So, I think the best thing to do here is to start by an example, right? So suppose we have
a tree, this time I will just show you a tree with ordered elements in it, so it's a search
tree. So you have a tree that looks like that, 9, and a child is 3, for example, and another
child is 1, that has leaves as its children, and then a child 3, that is 6, and then those
have leaves as children, and then 13, and then 11, and then 17, let's say. Suppose we want
to define a function that gives us the set of elements in this tree, okay? So how would
we do that? So firstly, recall. Well, before I do that formally, perhaps now, perhaps let
me just do another function. So how do we do this list with the list? So with the set
of elements. So here we want to compute the set of elements in this tree, which should
be 1, 3, 9, 11, 15, and 17, but of course there's not an order. So let me just write
the function actually, and then we can go through how to execute to understand the intuition.
So remember we did what we did with lists, so if you want to write, for example, a function
that gives you the set of elements in a list, which we call list set, we did it recur by
defining first the empty list case, and then the second one had this list, which was non-empty,
so the empty list was just empty, an empty set, and then the non-empty list returned
the insertion of x in list set of x's, if you recall. Okay, so how can we do that for the tree data
type? Recall that the tree datatype has those patterns, right? So datatype tree is either a
leaf or a node with a tree and another tree, so that's what we did last video, so this is a
reminder. So in order for us to write a recursion on that primitive recursive function, we need to
cover all the patterns, so I'll just call the function tree set, and this function has two
patterns to cover, right? The first one is the leaf, and in this case we return also an empty set,
and the second one is the node, which is a non-empty tree, so it has two sub-trees, so you have a node
in the left sub-tree, and an element in the right sub-tree, and then in this case this is going to
be like that, so insert A, and then tree set L union tree set R, okay? So just remove that so that's
clear, because it's pretty important, and then we can go through it, so insert A in set L union
tree set, and that's the correct parenthesis. Okay, so how, let me just show you how this
function will proceed in the same way we did with other recursive functions. So if we give this
function, if we run it on this tree as an example, what will it turn to us? So I will just evaluate it,
3 of that tree, which was 9, 3, 1, and 15, 11, 17. So the first time, this is the non-empty tree,
so it has, so we go into the second equation here, so what happens here is that we get insert 9
in tree of the left sub-tree, which is 3, 1, 6, union the right sub-tree, which is 15, 11, 17,
and that in turn will be insert 9, and the first one is again non-empty, so it's going to be insert
3 into 1, so here this one has two leaves as its children, so that union, all of that union,
then we close that, so insert 9 into 1, 2, 3, still, and the union, I will just write it 15,
11, 17, etc. So as you can see, it's going to return the correct set of elements,
but it's a bit of work if we want to do it manually, but that's basically the idea of
writing recursions on trees.